Guide to the Jack Sydow papers 1933-2001 (bulk dates 1942-1945) PR289
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Jack Sydow Photographs and Papers Collection
ca. 1933-2001 (bulk dates 1942-1945)
PR289
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
2.5 Linear feet (3 boxes)
This collection contains photographs and documents of Jack Sydow - actor, director, playwright, and professor. The items in the collection span the majority of Sydow's life, with a concentration on his time serving in the military during World War II and acting in the soldier show Hump Happy, and on his later theater career.
Related Materials at the New-York Historical Society
For additional materials related to the entertainment of WWII troops, see the
Radio Entertainers and Announcers Collection
.
The N-YHS Library's collection of World War II related materials can be searched using the
online catalog
.
Scope and Content Note
This collection of photographs, correspondence, and documents spans the majority of Jack Sydow's life. The bulk of the collection is from 1942-1945 when Sydow was serving in the military in World War II and acting in the traveling soldier show Hump Happy. The WWII portion of the collection contains letters Sydow wrote to his family, photographs, articles, and other documents relating to Sydow's travels and shows. The rest of the collection spans Sydow's adult life with a heavy focus on his theater career, and includes personal and stage photographs, play ephemera, and song books.
Biographical Note
Jack Sydow – actor, director, playwright, and professor – was born John David Sydow in Rockford, Illinois, 1921. Sydow served in the military in World War II with the Air Transport Command. While stationed in Assam, India, Sydow and fellow ATC enlisted men created a variety show Hump Happy, named for the range of mountains separating India and China referred to as "The Hump." The show featured Sydow dressed as a woman in a delayed-peel act and as one of the singing Andrew’s Sisters. Hump Happy traveled to military bases in India, the Middle East, and Africa, becoming the first soldier show to travel across combat areas.
Sydow graduated from the University of Illinois and received his master’s from Yale School of Drama. He continued to work in theater as an actor, director, and playwright throughout his life, receiving an Obie award for a theatrical adaptation in 1958 and a Tony award nomination for directing in 1966. From 1970 to 1986, Sydow was on the University of Washington School of Drama faculty, where he served as executive director and head of the directing program.
After retiring from the University of Washington, Sydow moved to Los Angeles where he continued to act both on the stage and in television. Sydow passed away in Los Angeles in 2010 at the age of 88.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series.
Series I: World War II, includes photographs and documents from Sydow's life while enlisted.
Series II: Life and career, includes photographs and documents from Sydow's life and career outside the military.
Provenance
Donated to the New-York Historical Society by J. Riley Caldwell-O'Keefe, PhD in 2012.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
References
Ford, Corey and Alastair MacBain. “Flying Strip Tease.” Collier’s, November 18, 1944.
“Jack Sydow: Obituary.” Rockford River Star, June 28, 2010. Accessed July 23, 2012. http://www.legacy.com/obituaries/rrstar/obituary.aspx?n=jack-sydow&pid=143765026#fbLoggedOut
Berson, Misha. “Memorial Set for UW’s Jack Sydow.” The Seattle Times, June 16, 2010. http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/thearts/2012135909_sydow17.html
Theater -- United States; United States. Army Air Forces. Air Transport Command; World War, 1939-1945
- Series I: World War II, 1942-1945, undated
  - Subseries I.1: Photographs
    Arrangement note
    Photographs have been arranged by subject into photographs of shows Sydow was involved in and photographs of travel and military life during his enlistment. Within the subject areas, photographs are arranged primarily by size. The numbers on the backs of each photograph correspond to an inventory created by Dr. J. Riley Caldwell-O'Keefe and are not indicative of original order.
    - Military and travel photographs, ca. 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Military and travel photographs, ca. 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Show photographs, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Scope and Contents note
      Shows include Hump Happy and Who Was That Lady, possibly others.
  - Subseries I.2: Correspondence
    - Sydow to his family, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Sydow to his family, 1943 January-June 3 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Sydow to his family, 1943 June 24-July (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Sydow to his family, 1943 August-December (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Sydow to his family, 1944 January-May (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Sydow to his family, 1944 June-December (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Sydow to his family, 1945 January-June (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Sydow to his family, 1945 July-December (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Subseries I.3: Documents
    - Newspaper clippings, 1944-1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Scope and Content Note
      Contains clippings about Hump Happy, obituaries for soldiers, and a French paper.
    - Show documents and ephemera, 1943-1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Includes posters, fliers, handwritten lyrics, a newsletter, and a letter from Anita Loos.
    - City guides and army badges, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Contains city guides to Madras and Calcutta published for U.S. soldiers and Sydow's army badges, including the China Burma India insignia.
    - Magazines, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Contains multiple copies of Collier's from Nov. 18, 1944 and Yank from Feb. 11, 1944. Magazines contain articles about Hump Happy.
- Series II: Life and career, 1933-2001, undated
  - Subseries II.1: Photographs
    Although the majority of the photographs are undated, they appear to span Sydow's adult life. Photographs of Sydow include professional portraits and personal photographs of Sydow both alone and with friends. Photographs of shows include shows that Sydow acted in as well as shows that Sydow directed.
    As the majority of the photographs are undated, they have been arranged by topic (either photographs of Sydow, photographs of shows, or miscellaneous). The photographs of Sydow and of shows have been further divided into black & white and color photographs. Within these divisions photographs are arranged primarily according to size, although an attempt was made to group like photographs together and to arrange them in rough chronological order, based primarily on guesswork.
    - Sydow - black and white photographs, 1947-52, 1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Sydow - black and white photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Sydow - black and white photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Sydow - black and white photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Sydow - color photographs, ca. 1970-1992, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Sydow - color photographs, ca. 1994-2001, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Shows - black and white photographs - identified, ca. 1948-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Shows included: Oh, Coward!, Glass Menagerie, The Late Christopher Bean, The Crucible, John Brown's Body, A Touch of the Poet, Once Upon a Mattress, and The Imaginary Invalid.
    - Shows - black and white photographs - identified, ca. 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Photographs and documents from Adding Machine. Originally housed in a photo album.
    - Shows - black and white photographs - unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Shows - black and white photographs - unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Shows - black and white photographs - unidentified, 1957, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Shows - color photographs - identified, ca. 1993 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Photographs from Shadowlands.
    - Shows - color photographs - unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Other unidentified photographs, 1933, 1943, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Subseries II.2: Documents
    - Play ephemera, 1939-1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Includes newspaper clippings and playbills.
    - Miscellaneous documents and drawings, 1942, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Stage plans, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Stage plans for The Matchmaker.
    - Song books, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)